He went back to the agency and told them
"Destroy all the documents." And I said,
half jokingly, "So, where are the
aliens?"
And he laughed and he said, "That is and
many, many nights after that
was just a man's voice
saying
eight
three
six. And then somebody at the CIA said,
"We've got to smuggle this into the
Soviet Union. How do you do that?"
Well, we could do it by hearing this
meeting and a determination is made that
yes, we're going to do this. We're going
to call it MK Ultra. And she said, "It's
all about weapons sales."
All of these meetings. We found
Nordine's head on the roof of the next
door neighbor's house. I hate coming off
as a conspiracy theorist, but and I
believe very strongly that the Israelis
knew exactly what was going to happen,
exactly when it was going to happen. We
created chaos in Iraq and chaos in Syria
and chaos in Libya and now chaos in
Iran. This isn't anything that's new.
It's been going on for more than a
century. I was with him for the first 56
consecutive hours of his captivity. I
tied him to the hospital bed. He had
surgery. Oh my god, I could talk about
this for the next 2 hours.
>> All right, welcome to Jason Alousis
Guys. Thank you for joining me today. We
have an esteemed guest, somebody that I
consider a true patriot and a hero.
We have with us John Kiriakou. You've
probably seen him all over the podcast
blowing up everywhere in the last few
months. He is a former Central
Intelligence Agency officer,
whistleblower, journalist, author, and
now podcaster. And he joins me today to
talk about how the world really works,
the myths and realities of espionage.
We're going to talk about history. We're
going to talk about current topics.
John, how are you?
>> I'm well, thanks, Jay. How are you?
>> Good. We had a a good time talking
before and so I thought, man, this guy
really knows his stuff. I've listened to
I don't know how many hours of you in
the last
in the last several months. And it's so
weird because when you listen to
somebody over and over and over on the
internet, you start to feel like, "Oh,
yeah, I know that guy." But you don't
actually know that guy. So,
there is a sort of familiarity. And of
course, we do have a lot of things in
common.
Let's start it off with some notes that
I jotted down after listening to a lot
of the recent interviews that you've
done. Of course, guys, you did just
appear on Tucker, and I think that went
up yesterday or the night before. Yeah,
and
>> So, be be sure and check that out.
John's channel is of course linked. And
he does his channel Deep Focus. And
let's start with something that's a
little spicy from the outset. I hear a
lot of former CIA people, pro-CIA
people, present CIA people, they they do
a sort of apologetic, which I
understand.
But they argue that the West and the CIA
never really engaged in sexual espionage
or that kind of operation because of the
legalities that it would interfere with
and the the the the rights that people
have. But we hear all kinds of stories
as well about Operation Midnight Climax,
where this is kind of farmed out to, you
know, the organized crime and this kind
of stuff. And we hear about Epstein and
the possible connections with various
intelligence agencies throughout the
world. So, is it a situation where it's
not on the books, but it's done kind of
on the side? Can you speak to that?
>> Oh, yeah, I can speak to it. Um
the CIA, since its inception, has been
involved in sexual operations, sexual
espionage. Certainly, sex was was a
well-documented component of MK Ultra,
which lasted from about 1952
to 1975. People are going to jump on my
head for saying it ended in 1975. It
ended in 1975.
Certainly, there are other operations
that could be considered successors to
MK Ultra, but MK Ultra ended in '75. You
talked about Operation Midnight Climax.
That's one of the more famous ones. It's
one of those operations that we talk
about today in 2026 and you just have to
shake your head and and ask
semi-rhetorically, "What in the world
were they thinking?"
But yeah, I mean sex was used routinely
well into the late '70s, the early '80s.
One of the very first questions, Jay,
that I asked when I joined not not the
CIA, but when I joined operations, which
was about halfway through my CIA career,
was about the use of honeypots, right?
Because when you're when you're learning
counterintelligence,
you learn how the Russians use
honeypots, the Israelis use honeypots.
Well, what about us?
And
one of my instructors, who became my
mentor, quite a famous officer, Gust
Avrakotos, he was played by Philip
Seymour Hoffman in the film Charlie
Wilson's War. Gust told me, "We used sex
all the time until Ronald Reagan became
president." And and not we didn't stop
because Ronald Reagan became president,
but roughly that period, only because it
just didn't work after a while. If you
really want somebody to be a source for
you and to commit espionage for you over
the course of, you know, years,
that relationship has to be built on a
foundation of trust, not one of
coercion.
And so, you know, if you go up to
somebody and say, "Listen, we set you up
with a prostitute the other night and
you didn't know, but we had the room
wired for video and audio and we have
these pictures of you and videos and
we're going to release them to your wife
or we're going to release them to your
government unless you work for us."
That's not how you build trust. That's
not how you build a long-term
relationship. And then he told me a
story, it very well could be apocryphal,
but I've I've always believed it. And
that was before the Iranian Revolution,
there was an Ayatollah that we wanted to
recruit. And so we sent a prostitute to
kind of bump him and lure him into um
into a a hotel and he had sex with her
and we took pictures and video and then
laid it out in front of him and said,
"We've got you."
And he laughed and he said, "I'll take
that in an 8x10 and give me two 5x7s of
this one." And he's like, "What's wrong
with you guys?
Seriously? Like in the movies, you're
going to try to threaten me? Get out of
here."
And it was around that operation that a
decision was made that this just isn't
working. If the Israelis and the
Russians think it works for them, that's
fine for them, but we just stopped doing
it.
>> Well, that's interesting because, you
know, when when we look into Epstein and
then the files and the emails and all
these dumps that that recently came out,
you know, there was quite a bit. I don't
know if you had have any time to read
like Whitney Webb's book. I thought it
was
>> Oh, yeah, Whitney Webb is terrific.
>> Whitney's book was great and I think she
demonstrates, you know, that this is
sort of a a copy-paste operation going
back to Robert Maxwell and then whoever
perhaps recruited Robert Maxwell, be the
Rothschilds or whoever into doing it and
and taught him the ropes. It seems like
that situation was relying very heavily
on compromise. Many of the the details
in the emails that are still somewhat
ambiguous and hard to figure out, they
seem to point in that direction.
I remember somebody saying
maybe it was Andrew Bustamante on a
video or something. But somebody was
saying something like, "Well, once you
do this, you kind of you can never do
anything with them again because they're
up forever going to hate you. So, you're
not, like you said, building trust. It
kind of kind of maybe as a last resort.
Is that why they would rely on something
like that for, you know, so many
politicians and members of Congress? Is
it Is it a last resort or is it a first
resort for some some countries?
>> You know, I I can give you an educated
guess and I'm going to say that it's
probably a first resort for a lot of
countries. It's unusual for me to agree
with something that Andrew Bustamante
has to say, but he I think he's right
about that. And then coming back to
something that you said just a moment
ago, we have to also consider the use of
cutouts.
So, that the chance of blowback
is lessened. And what I mean by that is
why would you set someone up in a
compromising sexual position and risk
it going bad and then having that
blowback on you when you can have
a cutout do it. You can have Jeffrey
Epstein do it. You can have a foreign
intelligence service do it for you or
an organized criminal gang or something
that doesn't point back to the CIA. You
know, look at it this way, too. We
learned so much from this latest tranche
of the Epstein documents, so much. And
there are still three to three and a
half million pages that the president is
now saying will not be released
apparently because they would embarrass
friends of his. But we now know that
Jeffrey Epstein apparently
was an access agent for the Israelis,
but that he had also volunteered
to work for the CIA, to work for the
FBI, to work for the British MI5 and the
British MI6 and the Germans, and that he
had tried repeatedly to get a private
one-on-one meeting with Vladimir Putin.
He couldn't quite get the meeting, but
the Russians offered a meeting with
Putin and two security officials, which
Epstein had turned down. So I think that
the answer to your question is most
likely yes, that this is going on, that
it always has gone on, and if it wasn't
a direct
CIA operation to use sex to to gather
information,
it was a CIA operation to use a cutout
to use sex to get information.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, I think oftentimes people think of
this as something that's only a
government agency, as if it couldn't be
Yeah, as if it couldn't be farmed out to
organized crime. You know, you
You know, you watch The Godfather and
The Godfather
You you they they get the politician at
one of the the Corleone's whorehouses.
So,
So, they got their you know, they got
the blackmail that they needed in that
situation. So, yeah, I think that's a
great point is you know, the use of
cutouts. And And I don't mean to go too
much into Hollywood and movies. My wife
and I were watching Peaky Grinders.
That's a joke, but making fun of a guy
that's Peaky Blinders.
There was a situation where you know,
the British government with SIS at that
time I guess was working with
you know, Cillian Murphy's or Irish
criminal gang. And together they're
having to combat the IRA and the
communists and they're using the
organized crime some in some cases to to
do a hit.
And I remember reading in some of the
books on Operation Underworld and some
of the stories of you know, the Genovese
crime syndicate after World War I
that the US intelligence apparatus at
that time was even kind of making links
with with organized crime. How
significant and real do you believe
those links were to the underground
world of organized crime from the
American intelligence apparatus over the
the decades of the 20th century. Is it
over is it exaggerated? Is that
something that is very important?
>> Strong. And with the advent of the
Freedom of Information Act and mandatory
declassification laws, we now have more
details about some of these
relationships. As you correctly pointed
out, the FBI worked very closely with
the Genovese family to secure the Port
of Brooklyn and the Port of Newark
during the Second World War. We know how
many different times the CIA worked with
the Santo Trafficante family in Tampa to
try to assassinate Fidel Castro. There
are other examples too. I have to be
careful here. Well, you know, an obvious
one from the 1980s
is when the CIA was working with
the Pablo Escobar cartel to target
communist separatists in Colombia in the
jungle. DEA was doing one thing, CIA is
doing exactly the opposite thing and
nobody saw any irony in that. There's a
famous case with a mob hitman, I think
he was a Colombo, named Greg Scarpa,
where Scarpa was recruited by the FBI to
go to Mississippi to find these three
freedom writers, Chapman, Chaney, I
forget the third one's name, who had
been murdered by the Ku Klux Klan, and
Scarpa actually kidnapped a clansman and
shot him in the knees to force him to
tell him where the bodies were, and
then, like magic, the FBI discovers the
bodies in an earthen dam outside of
town. So, yeah, you go through the
entire history, really, of the FBI and
the history of the CIA, and there are
lots of examples where they worked very
closely with organized crime.
>> Yeah, and that actually is a great
transition to the next topic I wanted to
ask you about, and that's Operation
Gladio, because Gladio's another example
of a very close connection between
Western intelligence agencies and
organized crime, particularly Sicilian
mafia, and what we know is as the P2
Lodge, or the Propaganda Due A Lodge in
Italy. And this was a post-World War II,
sort of, oddly enough, fascist-tending
a series of lodges that were able to be
sources for recruitment, according to
the public journalistic material that we
have, on the part of the CIA and other
outfits to sort of, again, recruit from
also organized crime. We have the
character Michele Sindona, and we have
the character Licio Gelli. And that ties
into secret societies as well as Masonic
networks, things like that. Is Gladio a
huge component of that post-World War II
alliance with the Vatican and Vatican
bank structure, or is this exaggerated?
>> I always believed that what we've
learned publicly, let me preface this by
saying everything I learned about
Operation Gladio, I learned after I left
the CIA. It was in 1990 that the Italian
Prime Minister, and I think it was
Andreotti at the time, went public when
speaking to Parliament about Operation
Gladio. For your viewers who don't know
what Gladio is, it was an operation
hatched by the CIA, MI6, the Vatican,
and NATO
to leave
essentially sleeper agents behind right
at the end of World War II
and in the couple of years after just in
case of a Soviet invasion so that there
would be an intelligence structure in
place that could help the Western
services confront the Soviets. You know,
in retrospect, looking at it in 2026, it
seems kind of quaint. You know, the
thing of an interesting movie that
might, you know, get nominated for an
Academy Award or two. But back then it
was deadly serious.
Deadly serious. We really believed the
Soviets were going to invade Western
Europe. We really believed it. And so
people were scrambling to create an
intelligence infrastructure. Keep in
mind, too,
that the CIA and NATO weren't created
until 1947. So there was this period of
of about a year and a half from '45 to
early '47 where we were just winging it.
MI6 was sort of the preeminent
intelligence service in the Western
world, but the KGB being the preeminent
service in the Eastern world. And
President Truman's advisers were saying,
"Listen, we need to be prepared for a
Soviet invasion of Western Europe." And
so
Truman asked the British
to send MI6 officers to New York
to sit with Americans and to help us
create what he called a central
intelligence agency, a place where all
foreign intelligence could be collected
and analyzed.
You know, just as a kind of a funny
aside, all of this ended up happening as
part of what's called the National
Security Act of 1947. J. Edgar Hoover,
the the long, long time director of the
FBI, he was the head of the FBI for 40,
what, 48 years? He was strongly opposed
to the creation of the CIA and an NSC,
the National Security Council was also
created in that same National Security
Act of 1947. So, he was going around
Capitol Hill asking members of Congress
to vote against it. And this is exactly
the opposite of what President Truman
wanted. Truman got wind that
Hoover was working against passage of
the bill, and so he called Hoover in
and told Hoover, "You've got this all
wrong. This Central Intelligence Agency,
it's going to be a component of the FBI.
So, you'll be head of the FBI and of the
CIA."
And he said, "Oh." And he lifted his
objection. It was a lie, of course.
There was never any intention for the
CIA to be a division of the FBI. And
Hoover never forgave Truman for lying to
him. But we were scrambling in 1946
and early 1947. Finally, these MI6
officers came to New York.
They were met by Bill Donovan and
Prescott Bush and a handful of others
swells from, you know, Wall Street and
the OSS days. And with some, you know,
pads of paper, they came up with a
centralized intelligence service that we
called the CIA.
>> Yeah, it's a fascinating history. I
remember several texts that discuss the
extreme influence, I guess you could
say, from British intelligence on how to
structure it, how to set it up. Several
early figures were very well trained by
the British like Frank Wisner. Yeah,
he's a massive student. Yeah, a massive
student of British counterintelligence.
But in terms of like going back to
Gladio real quick, a lot of writers
conceive of this as a template,
something that is not just about, you
know, setting up networks within Europe
that would stave off a Soviet NKVD style
takeover, but also perhaps train terror
cells that could be activated later on.
Now, we know that perhaps Gladio
probably ended, but maybe other types of
operations or templates that some
authors, I think Doug Valentine and
others connect Yeah, they connect these
types of operations to the template
of Iran-Contra training, you know, the
right-wing death squads there. And also
ISIS al-Qaeda type training that you
would get under Brzezinski and Carter
and Gates in the late '70s, early '80s
for the Soviet situation. Do you think
that's accurate? Is that exaggerated? Is
it a template that's used? One last
point, I remember reading Miles
Copeland's book Game of Nations and he
was discussing that
in his time in Egypt and in Syria when
he was a consultant
to the governments there. Obviously, he
says I was working for the CIA. He says,
"We would use terrorists all the time."
He says they're they're great patsies
and dupes. I'm not saying that the CIA
runs every terror operation, but he says
it's a very useful tool in the toolkit.
Is that accurate? Is this exaggerated as
well? Is it a template, a way to
structure Iran-Contra, ISIS, Gladio?
>> Oh, yeah. No, it's not exaggerated. And
I would actually take issue with his
statement that they're dupes. They're
not dupes. They're partners.
They're compensated handsomely. You bank
a favor that way.
>> Well, I I think he's saying the person
who goes in and actually blows himself
up is the dupe.
>> Oh, totally.
>> But maybe the handlers are are not
dupes.
>> No, no. I I'm with you on that. Yes, I
misunderstood. Uh yeah, that that would
be the the dupe. I mean, even somebody
like me, that that was not really my
world at the CIA. I was strictly a
counterterrorism officer. But even I had
contact with organized crime overseas.
We didn't give each other the warm and
fuzzies and we didn't invite each other
to dinner at each other's homes or
introduce each other to our respective
wives, but we shook hands and money
exchanged hands and I got what I wanted
and he got what he wanted and then we
never saw each other again. That's
actually quite a common event. There's
risk, of course, because you're dealing
with people who, you know, in some cases
are stone-cold killers and you need to
trust them to a point where they do what
you're paying them to do. The initial
encounters what's the most dangerous I
think. I I have told the story I was
dealing with a with an organized crime
figure overseas in the Middle East and
there was a French intelligence officer
dealing with him as well. And the French
intelligence officer one day was just
found dead in a ditch on the side of the
road. And so we had to all meet like
should I go to the next meeting? Are
they going to kill me at the next
meeting? I don't know. I said I don't
think he's going to kill me. I think he
trusts me. So I go to the next meeting.
It was very tense. It turned out to be
our last meeting and as I was walking
out he says to me, "Oh, by the way." And
I turned and I looked at him and he
said, "Your French friend very bad
tradecraft."
And I wasn't really sure what to make of
that other than the fact that he was
admitting to me that he had killed the
French intelligence officer. I don't
know why he didn't try to kill me.
But yeah, that kind of thing happens all
the time. It's It's a calculated risk
that you take. And you know, if the gain
the potential gain is greater than the
potential risk, sure you go forward and
you're very happy to meet with
criminals.
>> In regard to to terror, again you being
expert at the sale on counterterrorism,
dealing with that. I think we in the
world of alternative media we tend to
think immediately when you see when you
hear the word terror you immediately
think false flag. You think staged. You
think engineered. Certainly not every
event is staged or engineered something
like that. There are organic believers
in radical ideologies. But we also have
this reality too of false flag events.
If we were to think back of the last say
century or last several decades, how
many instances would you guess? Or if
you had to do a percentage or something
just speculation, right? Like do you
think most major terror events have a
kind of connection to a state or to some
other type of entity or or is it
organic?
>> No, that's a good That's a good
question.
That's a tough question. You know what?
I'm going to have to say Oh, I'm going
to take a lot of [__] for this. I'm
going to have to say
that yes, I think most of them probably
are connected to a state in some way.
I hate coming off as a conspiracy
theorist, but when you dig down into
some of these operations,
I mean, look at 9/11. I mean, 9/11 was
carried out by Al-Qaeda. We know that.
I'm 1,000%
confident 9/11 was carried out by
Al-Qaeda. But who was behind Al-Qaeda?
Clearly, it was the Saudi government.
And I believe very strongly that the
Israelis knew exactly what was going to
happen, exactly when it was going to
happen, but it was to Israel's benefit
that the United States be attacked so
that the US would respond by killing 2
million Muslims over the next 20 years,
which is exactly what we did. We created
chaos in Iraq, and chaos in Syria, and
chaos in Libya, and now chaos in Iran,
and that's to Israel's benefit. So, I
think in many, many cases,
yeah, there's a state behind it. And
I'll add one thing. I've talked about
this publicly many times, but that on
the night that we captured Abu Zubaydah
in March of 2002, we caught him in a in
a safe house in Faisalabad, Pakistan.
One of the things that we confiscated
that night was his diary.
And so,
I was with him for the first 56
consecutive hours of his captivity. I
tied him to the hospital bed. He had
surgery to treat three gunshot wounds.
We shot him when the Pakistani shot him
while he was trying to escape that
night. And so, I was so sleepy, I was
afraid I was going to fall asleep and he
was going to escape somehow. So, I tore
up a sheet, I tied him to the bed.
And I'm just sitting there at the foot
of the bed like this, just kind of
staring at him for most of the 56 hours.
But one of the things that we
confiscated that night in the raid was
his diary.
And so, I started leafing through the
diary.
And it made my hair stand up. Most of it
was silly. Most of it was doodles. He
was an accomplished sketch artist.
Like I would pay money for some of the
drawings that he did.
>> It would have been funny if the doodles
were like a like a high school teenage
girl's doodles.
>> Right, right.
With hearts over the letter I and stuff
like that. No.
>> [laughter]
>> Um
>> Terrorist Terrorist with a heart of
gold.
>> Seriously. Misunderstood. He wrote a lot
of poetry,
much of it which was quite good. He
wrote
letters to his younger self, which I
found fascinating. And this led to a
split between the CI and the FBI where
the FBI said he was a madman.
And the CIA said, "No, he's he's
extraordinarily intelligent." The CIA
turned out to be correct on that. He
would write these letters to himself
like it was the the 27-year-old Abu
Zubaydah
or the or the 30-year-old Abu Zubaydah
writing to the 14-year-old Abu Zubaydah
saying, "Treat our mother with respect.
You were rude to her today. Don't
whistle at those girls. You're a Muslim
Muslim, you shouldn't whistle at girls."
You know, stuff like that.
But
what I also saw in the diary were three
cell phone numbers.
And they were to three members of the
Saudi royal family.
Why in God's name would
someone that we believed at the time was
the number three in Al-Qaeda? He wasn't
the number three, but he was a bad guy.
He had established and staffed
Al-Qaeda's two training camps in
southern Afghanistan as well as
Al-Qaeda's safe house in Peshawar, the
house of martyrs. Why would he have the
personal cell phone numbers of three
Saudi princes?
And so we went to the Saudis and we
said, "Take care of this or we're going
to take care of it and you're not going
to like the way we take care of it."
The next thing you know,
one of these princes dies on the
operating table during bariatric
surgery. They're all fat pigs.
>> They're all fat pigs.
>> The second prince is killed in a one-car
accident on the Riyadh to Jeddah
highway.
And the third prince goes camping in the
desert and dies of thirst.
So,
yeah.
That tells me that the last thing they
wanted was for the CIA to snatch these
guys and to start interrogating them.
Which then, of course, led me to believe
that the Saudi government was involved
in 9/11.
>> Yeah. I mean,
so many things point that way.
>> We even had that it was a 16 pages of
Yeah, it turns out the Saudi Yeah, the
20 Yeah, that the Saudis did have a key
role, turns out, which many people
theorized and suspected. And that's our
ally, right? That's not a you know,
terrorist state, but it's supposedly
also one of the greatest funders.
But it's a funder of terror, right?
>> Yeah.
>> On the topic of
Saudi Arabia, and I don't want to get
too far afield, but it just made me
think of this. I remember reading
recently that Kissinger, back in the
1970s, had a very important role
in restructuring how the petrodollar
would function in the world, and that
there was an intentional shifting away
from using US oil or native oil here to
put us in reliance on foreign oil, like
Saudis and others,
to give us then an excuse to I thought
this was a really
cunning genius sort of conspiracy plot
here. Of a villain [laughter] plot. So,
now that Now we have an excuse for
foreign policing because we're tied to
the oil that we get from all these other
countries. And we heard recently with
Trump, right, that we've got to do all
this for the We have to get the oil.
We've got the the British oil. There's
oil that we've got to
>> We take the oil. We've got to take the
oil.
>> Well, don't we have a lot of oil here? I
thought Trump ran on that, right? We've
got so much oil here.
>> We're sitting on an ocean of oil.
>> an ocean of oil. But now we have to
police the world over oil. Is it a
plausible theory that Kissinger, and
I've heard read via the Bilderberg
meetings at that time, that they sort of
planned out the petrodollar as a excuse
for future world police.
>> I I think that's exactly what happened.
I think that's exactly what happened and
we're seeing still the effects today
50 years after that policy was enacted.
You know, I've got a friend, former CIA
friend
who left the CIA and went into he's a
he's one of these genius um engineers.
And so he left the CIA and he went to
work for one of the big oil companies.
And he said something to me that was so
interesting. He said, "It's not
cost-effective to frack for oil if oil
is at $60 a barrel or lower."
Okay, if it's over 60, fracking is
cost-effective, it's profitable,
everybody's going to want to do it.
Okay, well, oil is what? $110, $115 a
barrel right now.
And we're fracking a little bit.
But what are we doing with the fracked
oil?
We're sending it to Japan.
We sell all that oil to Japan. So, why
would we export our own oil and import
Middle Eastern oil?
>> Exactly.
>> Because that's exactly what we do. Well,
we do it to maintain that tie to the
Middle East.
And as much as I hate Henry Kissinger,
and I really do, the butcher of Cyprus,
the butcher of Chile, the butcher of
Cambodia, I hate Henry Kissinger.
He was telling us the truth when he said
that
that this policy as
as
as calculating and cunning as it may
seem, it's it's a reality of American
foreign policy.
It really is.
Yeah, and and let's see if you don't
mind, Jay, I
>> Oh, feel free.
>> to just to speak a minute about
Venezuela.
How does Venezuela fit in or not fit
into this? Venezuela is different, it's
separate. Venezuela's oil is is so
dirty.
It is so high in sulfur
that it can only be refined at specialty
refineries where they inject
tons of chemicals to try to purify it.
Even still, you can't purify it enough
to turn it into gasoline. Right? And and
these
these refineries exist
right now for the most part only in
South Florida. The Chinese built one
recently, the Indians built one, but for
the most part, the only refineries that
can handle this really dark heavy oil
are in Florida.
And the oil is used only for home
heating oil.
So, when we talk about oil and
international oil and OPEC, of which
Venezuela is a member, we have to keep
Venezuela sort of off to the side
because it's a different issue from a
foreign policy perspective.
>> Yeah, that's a great point, too, because
we don't think about these different
regions having very very different ways
that they fit into the global, you know,
system. But, I do want to ask you, too,
about briefly here because you had such
a There's so many places we could go.
You've had such an adventuresome life,
and I've listened to you many times tell
the stories of when you were stationed
in Greece and you were dealing with
the left. And the first thing that came
to my mind was in in the case of these
leftist organizations, that one of which
I think tried to have you unalived,
shall we say? And feel free to rehearse
that story if you'd like, because I
think this audience may not have heard
it, but
the first thing that comes to my mind
when I hear this kind of stuff is who
funds these things? Like, I've never
even heard of this left Greek this
organization that was radical left. And
we always look to the money to see, you
know, who's funding this, who's pushing
this. Who would fund such a thing and
why would it be Soviet? You know, I
mean, the Cold War is kind of coming to
an end. Like, who would be behind that?
>> Oh my god, I could talk about this for
the next 2 hours. I'm going to make it
short. So, the group you're talking
about is called Revolutionary
Organization 17 November.
In October of 1975,
the CIA named a new station chief in
Athens. His name was Richard Welch.
Dick Welch was a Philhellene. He was a
lover of all things Greek. He had a
degree in the classics. He spoke ancient
Greek. He spoke modern Greek. He got a
master's degree in archaeology. This guy
just loved loved loved everything
Greece.
And he's named CIA station chief in
Athens. So, he arrives.
Six weeks later
on December 23rd, 1975, he's invited to
the US ambassador's Christmas party.
He and his wife go to the ambassador's
Christmas party in their
chauffeur-driven car.
They have a good time by all accounts.
And at the end of the party, they drive
back to their house.
In a very close-in very high-end suburb
of Athens called Psychiko. [music]
These are the days before automatic door
openers or gate openers. So, the driver
pulls up to the gate and gets out of the
car to open the gate to drive into the
property.
There's a car parked directly across the
street. There are three men and a woman
inside the car.
We never identified the woman.
Two of the men get out of the car and
one of them shouts in Greek, Richard
Welch, get out of the car.
Dick gets out of the car and Mrs. Welch
gets out of the car. The driver runs for
his life.
One of the men says, Richard Welch, you
have been found guilty of crimes against
the Greek people and you've been
sentenced to death. And then shoots him
three times in the chest with a .45
caliber semi-automatic handgun that
became known as the Welch .45. They
killed 18 more people with that same gun
between 1975 and 2002.
They then got back in the car and drove
away.
The Greek police were so inept
that the killers had to call the cops a
week ago and say, you idiots, the
getaway car we left abandoned at the
intersection of this street and that
street. Go get it.
In the meantime,
the killers wrote a manifesto. Now, this
became a theme. They would write a
manifesto at almost every attack over
the next 27 years.
But this manifesto they
they sent to a sympathizer in Paris.
And the sympathizer in Paris
hand-delivered it to the French
philosopher Jean-Paul Sartre.
Sartre read it and said, "What is this
craziness?" And he literally put it in a
desk drawer and forgot about it.
A year later,
the former chief of the Greek National
Police,
a man named Mallios,
he had been the chief of the Greek
National Police during the military
dictatorship, and he was a he was a
deeply hated torturer.
He would leave his apartment every
single day at the same time
and buy a newspaper and go to the coffee
shop and drink coffee.
And this one day in April of 1976,
he came out of his apartment. There was
a man and a woman there
making out.
And he told us later
on his deathbed
that he smiled when he saw them and he
thought to himself, "Young love in the
spring."
As soon as he walked past them, the man
pulled out the Welch 45 and shot him
three times in the back.
He lived for 2 hours.
And the description he gave of the
shooter matched Mrs. Welch's description
of the shooter in her husband's
assassination.
They sent another manifesto to Jean-Paul
Sartre.
So, Sartre receives it. Actually, Sartre
didn't receive it. Bernard-Henri Lévy,
who is today France's most famous
philosopher and poet and was Sartre's
assistant at the time, he said, "Wait a
minute. We've received something like
this before."
And he found the original one
in the desk. And then he sent them both
to Liberation newspaper. It's the
leftist newspaper in Paris. They
published them. That put 17 November on
the map. 17 November was named after the
date in 1974
when there was a student uprising at the
Athens Polytechnic University where the
military dictatorship in its final death
throws open fire with tanks on unarmed
students. And to hear the students tell
it killed 500. To hear the fascist tell
it they killed three dozen. We'll never
know. They destroyed most of the bodies.
But that put 17 November on the map. And
you ask a very, very important question.
Where did they get the money?
We just assumed in 1975 that these guys
were tied to the KGB.
But we had a long-standing agreement
with the KGB. You don't kill our guys
and we don't kill your guys. We try to
recruit each other's guys, but no
killing.
And the the Russians came to us and they
said, "Listen, this was not us.
It just was not us." And then the
Bulgarians proactively came to us and
said, "We promise this was not us and we
can tell you it was not the Soviets."